The President: My fellow Americans,
a short time ago,
I ordered the United
States Armed Forces
to launch precision strikes
on targets associated with
the chemical weapons
capabilities of Syrian dictator
Bashar al-Assad.
A combined operation with
the armed forces of France
and the United Kingdom
is now underway.
We thank them both.
Tonight, I want to speak
with you about
why we have taken this action.
One year ago, Assad launched
a savage chemical weapons attack
against
his own innocent people.
The United States responded
with 58 missile strikes
that destroyed 20
percent of the Syrian Air Force.
Last Saturday, the Assad
regime again deployed
chemical weapons to
slaughter innocent
civilians -- this time, in
the town of Douma,
near the Syrian capital
of Damascus.
This massacre was a
significant escalation
in a pattern of
chemical weapons use
by that very terrible regime.
The evil and the
despicable attack
left mothers and fathers,
infants and children,
thrashing in pain
and gasping for air.
These are not the actions
of a man;
they are crimes of
a monster instead.
Following the horrors of
World War I a century ago,
civilized nations joined
together to ban chemical warfare.
Chemical weapons are
uniquely dangerous
not only because they inflict
gruesome suffering,
but because even small amounts
can unleash
widespread devastation.
The purpose of our actions
tonight is to establish
a strong deterrent against
the production, spread,
and use of
chemical weapons.
Establishing this deterrent is
a vital national security interest
of the United States.
The combined American, British,
and French response
to these
atrocities will integrate
all instruments of
our national power --
military, economic,
and diplomatic.
We are prepared to sustain
this response
until the Syrian regime
stops its use
of prohibited chemical agents.
I also have a message tonight
for the two governments
most responsible for supporting,
equipping, and financing
the criminal Assad regime.
To Iran, and to Russia, I ask,
what kind of a nation wants
to be associated with
the mass murder of innocent men,
women, and children?
The nations of the world
can be judged
by the friends they keep.
No nation can succeed in
the long run
by promoting rogue states,
brutal tyrants,
and murderous dictators.
In 2013, President Putin
and his government promised
the world that
they would guarantee
the elimination of Syria's
chemical weapons.
Assad's recent attack --
and today's response --
are the direct result of
Russia's failure
to keep that promise.
Russia must decide if it
will continue down
this dark path, or if it will
join with civilized nations
as a force for
stability and peace.
Hopefully, someday we'll
get along with Russia,
and maybe even Iran
-- but maybe not.
I will say this, the United States
has a lot to offer,
with the greatest
and most powerful economy
in the history
of the world.
In Syria, the United
States -- with but a small
force being used to eliminate
what is left of ISIS --
is doing what is
necessary to protect
the American people.
Over the last year,
nearly 100 percent
of the territory once controlled
by the so-called ISIS caliphate
in Syria and
Iraq has been liberated
and eliminated.
The United States has also
rebuilt our friendships
across the Middle East.
We have asked our partners to
take greater responsibility
for securing their home region,
including contributing large
amounts of money
for the resources, equipment,
and all of the
anti-ISIS effort.
Increased engagement from
our friends,
including Saudi Arabia,
the United Arab Emirates, Qatar,
Egypt, and others can
ensure that Iran
does not profit from the
eradication of ISIS.
America does not seek an
indefinite presence
in Syria under no
circumstances.
As other nations step up
their contributions,
we look forward to the day
when we can bring
our warriors home.
And great
warriors they are.
Looking around our very
troubled world,
Americans have no illusions.
We cannot purge the world
of evil or act everywhere
there is tyranny.
No amount of American
blood or treasure can produce
lasting peace and
security in the Middle East.
It's a troubled place.
We will try to make it better,
but it is a troubled place.
The United States will be
a partner and a friend,
but the fate of the region
lies in the hands
of its own people.
In the last century, we
looked straight into
the darkest places of
the human soul.
We saw the anguish that
can be unleashed
and the evil that can take hold.
By the end of the World War I,
more than one million people
had been killed or injured
by chemical weapons.
We never want to see that
ghastly specter return.
So, today, the nations of
Britain, France,
and the United States of America
have marshaled
their righteous power against
barbarism and brutality.
Tonight, I ask all
Americans to say a prayer
for our noble warriors and
our allies as they carry out
their missions.
We pray that God will
bring comfort to those suffering
in Syria.
We pray that God will
guide the whole region
toward a future of
dignity and of peace.
And we pray that God will
continue to watch over
and bless the United
States of America.
Thank you, and goodnight.
Thank you.